<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The translation of a letter written by a Frenche gentilwoman to an other gentilwoman straunger, her frind, vpon the death of the most excellent and vertous ladye, Elenor of Roye, Princes of Conde, contaynyng her last wyll and testament. Doone by Henry Myddelmore gentylman at the request of the Ladye Anne Throkmorton</title>
            <author>I. D. V., fl. 1564.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1564</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14250</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24565</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105901</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841626</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841626</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6224</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14250)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6224)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1612:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The translation of a letter written by a Frenche gentilwoman to an other gentilwoman straunger, her frind, vpon the death of the most excellent and vertous ladye, Elenor of Roye, Princes of Conde, contaynyng her last wyll and testament. Doone by Henry Myddelmore gentylman at the request of the Ladye Anne Throkmorton</title>
                  <author>I. D. V., fl. 1564.</author>
                  <author>Myddelmore, Henry.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[66] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By John Daye, for Humfrye Toye, dwellyng in Paules churchyarde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Cum priuilegio Regiæ Maiestatis 1564.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: pi¹ A-D.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Condé, Éléonore, --  Princesse de, 1535-1564 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6224:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6224:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>THE TRANS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of a letter written by a Frenche
Gentilwoman to an other Gentilwoman ſtraunger, her frind, vpon the death of
the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and vertuous Ladye, Elenor of Roye, Princes of Conde,
contaynyng her laſt wyll and Teſtament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doone by Henry Myddelmore Gentyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man at the requeſt of the
Ladye Anne Throkmorton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶Imprinted at London by Iohn Daye, for Humfrye Toye, dwellyng
in Paules Churchyarde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio Regiae Maieſtatis, 1564.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6224:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6224:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <hi>The laſt wyl and</hi> Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament of the Princes
of Conde.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O ſoone as reaſon and gods worde mighte commaund mine eies,
and that this paper, watered ouer with my teares, mighte drye it ſelfe: I dyd
take my penne in hande to anſwere the requeſt that ſo inſtantlye you
made vnto me, to wrytte you a brief diſcourſe of the maner &amp; courſe
of my Ladye the Princes of Condes ſicknes: For the greate deſier you haue
(as you ſaye) that the ſhadowe of hyr death, maye ſerue you for a lighte
to lighten your doings, againſt the thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the darknes of oure lyfe in
this perillous pilgrimage. But I pray you (yf I do not ſatiſfice your
expectation accordynge to the ſufficiencye of the ſubiect) accuſe the
baſenes of my wytte rather then the good wyl I haue to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent you, and to
gyue by this priuate <pb facs="tcp:6224:3"/> letter (ſince better I cannot do it) a
faythfull teſtimonye of hyr vertue, which wel deſerueth a publike ſetting
forth. The prophane auncientes were wont to ſaye when they dyd loſe ſuche
patternes and examples of vertue, that God, beinge angrye wyth men, dyd beareft
them of ſo great a good before the tyme. And you ſhall gyue me leaue to
ſay to you, that in very conſcience I beleue he iudged vs vnworthye of a
thinge of ſo great valure.</p>
            <p>And nowe, leauynge to ſpeake of the reſte of hyr lyfe, &amp;
of the firſt and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt cauſes of hyr euell, that is to ſaye the
extreame ſorowes whiche ſhe was dryuen to deuoure, in that firſte
peryl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous tyme of the impriſonment of my Lorde the Prince hyr huſbande,
and lykewyſe of Madame de Roye hyr mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (the ſame being a right worthie
ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of a great hiſtorye, whereby might be eterniſed, and made
perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, the ſingular graces which God had endued this noble Princes
wyth, and the vnſpeakable force and conſtancye <pb facs="tcp:6224:3"/> of hyr mynde in
all hyr aduerſities) I wyll begynne with the moſt euidentes and
freſheſt.</p>
            <p>I doubt not, but you haue harde how that after ſhe had letfe my
Lord hyr huſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bande at Meaux (at the ſame tyme that he reſolued to goo to
Orlea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s) as ſhe was traualynge towardes hyr houſe, called Muret, and
paſſynge by a vyllage na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Vanderay, nere vnto Lizy &amp; vpon the ryuer
of Ours, a companye of pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants (whiche then were goinge in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion)
dyd ſet vpon hyr and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis of Conty hyr eldeſt ſonne, wyth
ſtaues, ſtones, croſſes and banners, and that without any occaſion
geuen, but that there was a malicious &amp; naughty prieſt emongeſt them,
who for the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred that he bare to the religion, incited &amp; ſet on the
ſayd troupe of paiſants ſo to outrage hyr and hyr companye, at this very
tyme the fyer of the troubles for religion did begynne to kyndle, and in the
moſte partes of all Fraunce the ſparkelles thereof dyd alreadye
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6224:4"/>Thys furor and populous rage, dyd ſo moue and
vnquiet this good Lady, that hauynge gonne to the ende of cyghte monethes,
ſhe was the ſame daye, by feare, and before hyr tyme, delyuered of two
boyes, at a village called Gandalu, before ſhe could recouer any of hyr owne
houſes. And within fewe dayes after (as ſhe was naturallye of greate
courage and harte) ſhe toke hyr waye towardes Orleans, to mete wyth my Lord
hyr huſbande: Whether ſhe came in the ende by longe and dangerous iourneis.
For you muſt imagine, that all the wayes and paſſages were alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye
taken and kepte. And that therfore ſhe was dryuen to vſe great
circumſpec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, and to expoſe hyr perſon to verye great daunger to make
that haſardous voiage.</p>
            <p>Note you that, of this ſame incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniencye: Of the ſecond
tyme of the impriſonment of my Lord hyr huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, after the cruell conflict
of a battail: Of the beſiegyng of the towne of Orleans, <pb facs="tcp:6224:4"/> and ſo
of the paynes and continuall trauailes, which ſhe dyd ſuffer &amp; abyde
duryng the whole tyme of the troubles (beſyde that ſhe dyd not diligentlye
inough loke to hyr ſelfe, when ſhe had the laſt yere the ſmale pokes at
Galleo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) hath growen and proceaded, by courſe of tyme, all hyr ſicknes and
indiſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But chyefly an Iſſue of bloud, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by a
Carcinome, or eatyng canker, in the Matrice: whiche hyr ſhamefaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and
chaſtitie, woulde neuer ſuffer to be dreſſed as it was requiſite and
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarye.</p>
            <p>This fluxe of bloud, which was faier, redde, and of good
ſubſtaunce, beganne the .xxvj. daye of April laſt paſt, but toke hyr
more aboundauntlye the thurſdaye and Sonday nexte followynge, and ſo
continued and lefte of, at certain times vntyll the .xxiij. daye of this
preſent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of Iuly: At what tyme hyr forces were ſo abated and
weakened, that ſhe loſt vtterly the power retentiue: ſo as the ſame
then runnyng oute vnto the <pb facs="tcp:6224:5"/> droppe of that lyttell that remayned of
the former great voydynges, ſhe yelded happelye vp hyr ſprite to God,
throughe lacke of natural heate, at Conde about xj. of the cloke in the
mornynge.</p>
            <p>This euacuation was very muche haſtened by a dyet whiche a
lyttell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe had taken in hande, and would nedes continue the ſame
after hyr re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne from Troye: where ſettinge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyde all other thynges,
ſhe had bene in great haſt to ſee my Lord her huſband, then newly,
fallen into a ſicknes: which dyet was cleane contrarye to hyr, &amp; the
drinke that ſhe toke dyd greatly heate &amp; chafe hyr bloud, whiche of it
ſelfe was ouer ſubtil. Herein I canne aſſure you that after the
Phiſitions and Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giens were ons made acquainted with all, they dyd omite
nothynge of that, that order and knowledge might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde: And it had bene
very eaſye at the beginnynge to haue remedyed and healed it, if the matter
had been ſo ſoone declared as it was requiſite.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6224:5"/>In the tyme of this ſicknes manye accidents
happened, as the laſke, the feuer Hetique, whiche was with ſome
acceſſe, payne of the raynes, with great vnquietnes, faintinges and
ſoundings throughe the venimous vapours caried from the diſeaſed part to
the ſtomacke, to the lyuer, to the harte, and to the braine. You muſte
thynke that I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne hardlye expreſſe vnto you all her griefs, for they were
by the iudgement of them that be moſt expert in that arte, ſo dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe
and violent, that they had bene vndurable to any other.</p>
            <p>Wherin, I pray you marke wel, how greatlye God dyd aſſiſt
and ſtrengthen her, for ſhe neuer opened her mouthe to murmur, nor made any
ſhewe or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce of impacience. I did alwayes ſee her in her
greateſt paines with drye eyes, without cryinge, without teares, and without
complaintes: whiche be ordinary to all ſicke folckes, yea to the moſt
ſtrongeſt and conſtants.</p>
            <p>And becauſe I knowe, it wylbe great pleaſure vnto you, to
heare me particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lariſe <pb facs="tcp:6224:6"/> ſomwhat of her behauiours, I wyl
ſhewe you, that the moſt egre and lamentable voice, that in all the time of
her ſicknes I euer harde her pronounce (and yet as you know I was very litell
from her) was that one tyme about an eyght dayes before her death, beynge
preſſed with extreme payne, ſhe addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her ſelfe to God, in
raiſing her voice a lyttell more then ſhe was accuſtomed (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe
could not fynde in two beddes with al her often chaungyngs, any one place where
ſhe might reſt one minute of an houre) and ſayde.</p>
            <p>Oh Lord God almightye, foraſmuch as in all the places of this
terreſtriall abydynge (how great and ſpacious ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it be, and wherof
thou arte onlye creatour) I cannot fynde by all my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence one littell
corner of quietnes nor voyde of grief (wherby I might ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally pronounce, as
I was wont, thy great goodnes and mercye) I leaue and gyue ouer wyllingly my
longer dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge and abode here, to retourne, yf it pleaſe thee, at this
tyme to that heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly <pb facs="tcp:6224:6"/> reſt whiche thou haſt prepared for me,
by the death and paſſion of thy welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued Sonne. Make my God my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
by his meanes, that my ſoule and body be both content and at reſt: The one,
to be free and at libertie goyng ſtraight to thee, who I ſee doth alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye
ſtretche out his armes for me: The other abydynge inſenſible here belowe,
vntyl thou doeſt waken it at the ſounde of thy commynge.</p>
            <p>I cannot tell whether this her talke wyll ſeame to you oute of
order or no, but I canne aſſure you I neuer harde her ſpeake worſe
wordes in the myddes of her greateſt extremities.</p>
            <p>This chaſt Ladye, for ſo I may right well cal her, as
accompliſhed in euerye degrée and in al circumſtaunces in that
excellent gifte and matronall modeſtie, whiche dyd followe her euen vnto her
graue, as you ſee Iuſtice doth Kynges to theyr buryals (wherof I requyre no
better prouffe then the very confeſſion of her ennemyes (and I do nothynge
maruell if in your countrey ſo manye <pb facs="tcp:6224:7"/> wyſe and graue Ladyes doe
determine to ſet her before their eyes, for an image &amp; mirrour of
chaſtitie in the brin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyng vp &amp; nurturynge of their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, euen as
we here emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt our ſelues deſire to do the lyke. For to ſpeake
tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, ſhe doth excell all thoſe that euer haue bene celebrated by any
hyſtorie: And at one worde there was neuer no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge that founde place in hyr
harte but vertue only: And therof I may be a ſufficient wittnes, hauynge had
the honor, euen from her cradell and moſt tender yeres, to be alwayes about
her perſonne.</p>
            <p>She, I ſay, dyd well forſee, ſo ſoone as this Iſſue of
bloud beganne to take her, that the diſeaſe was mortall: And beſydes her
owne iudgement (hauynge harde the opinion of them that had the charge of her
health) ſhe reſolued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continently to gyue order in her houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde
affaires, to th'intent ſhe mighte the more lyberallye thynke of God.</p>
            <p>And to this effect ſhe ſent for my Lorde the Prince her
huſbande, deſiryng hym <pb facs="tcp:6224:7"/> moſt humbly to come to her: which he
dyd forthwith and in great haſt, after he had receaued the newes thereof at
Vitry: from whence on the morow the court remoued to Bar.</p>
            <p>And after he had ben a two or three dayes at home with her, &amp;
that ſhe had made many chereful ſhewes and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the Ioye ſhe
had to ſee hym (for you knowe there was neuer wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that loued, cheryſhed,
honored, or reſpected more her huſbande then ſhe dyd hym) ſhe prayed
two perſonages, towardes the lawe, whiche ſhe knewe dyd loue and honor
theyr houſe, to goe and declare vnto hym the greate dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of death wherin
ſhe thought her ſelfe to be (fearynge it ſhoulde greue hym muche more if
ſhe her ſelfe dyd tell him it): To thyntent it mighte pleaſe hym to gyue
her leaue to ordeyne and diſpoſe of certaine thinges whiche ſhe deſired
to haue executed after her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe.</p>
            <p>And I do very well remember that when ſhe ſent theſe two
counſellors to <pb facs="tcp:6224:8"/> hym, ſhe deſired them to ſaye vnto hym
emongeſt all the reſt) theſe woordes whiche I dyd well note.</p>
            <p>Since, the good pleaſure of God was that the ſeparation of
hym, &amp; her ſhould be made as touchinge the body, yet ſhe deſired him
that theyr ſoules might con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinue together inſeparable, in that cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
which they dyd owe alike to theyr father Ieſus Chriſt: who had ſo
mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſlye deliuered them in the ſight of all the worlde, from ſo
many troubles and dangers as they had paſſed and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped by his grace:
That he had lefte vnto them children the ſure gage of theyr amitie: And that
to beginne her teſtament, ſhe dyd make hym vniuerſal inheritor of that
Maſſe of loue that ſhe had hitherto bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e them: To y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end that after her death he ſhold loue them both
for hym ſelfe and for her to: recomme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge them vnto hym principally for
their bringing vp and inſtruction in the feare of God: whiche ſhe
aſſured to be the moſt certaine good and patrimonie that ſhe coulde
leaue them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6224:8"/>They haue, ſayd ſhe, good beginnings, and that at
the handes of a ſufficient maſter (meanynge the miniſter de l'Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine)
who in dede hath of late taken great paynes with them, interpretynge vnto them
euery mornynge (with great dexteritie) the prouerbes of Salomon: And in the
afternone the Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> whereby my Lorde
Marquis theyr eldeſt ſonne hath ſo wel profited, that he is one of the
beſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that is to be founde of his age.</p>
            <p>She added vnto theſe (as ſhe was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes a well ſpoken
woman) manye other godly ſayenges &amp; exhortations: whiche the force of the
ſtreame that iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued out of myne eyes dyd lette me to beare awaye. And do
you not marueil at all, if I dyd then weepe ſo abounda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for the two
perſons before ſpoken of, dyd no leſſe, before they departed to goo
thether as ſhe had deſired them.</p>
            <p>Soone after I ſawe them retourne agayne to make reporte of the
honeſt &amp; wyſe talke, that my Lord the Prince had vſed vnto them vpon
this ſorowful <pb facs="tcp:6224:9"/> ſubiect: Wherof the good Ladye recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a
moſt greate contentation &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: And they both tolde me apart: that
it was impoſſible for any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpeake more eloquentlye then the Prince
had done to them (as euerye man knoweth how wel ſpoken he is, of how good
iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement he is, and howe gentil a Prince he is) True it is, ſaid they, that
we haue very wel perceaued, that the amitie and loue whiche he beareth to this
his dere ſpouſe &amp; compagnion, did oftentimes breake the thryd of his
Oration, by the many and depe ſighes he gaue, whiche doe ſufficientlye
wytnes his iuſt &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found ſorowe.</p>
            <p>God, ſayd he, who hath conioyned vs together, ſeparate &amp;
ſonder vs ſince it doth ſo pleaſe him: it is reaſon that we do wholly
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forme our ſelues to his holy wyl: It is certaine that he is more happy
that goeth to hym, then he that caryeth here and abydeth an other paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage:
Oh happye houre that God ſhal ordayne vs to be reunited in heauen, in the
place of euerlaſtinge felicitie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6224:9"/>In the meane tyme, I wyll ſtudye to kepe wel the
gages which ſhe hath lefte me, and wyl continue them in the ſame maner of
teachinge that ſo chriſtianlye they haue begonne, to thintent, that the
vſe and the propertie of the mother, of the father, and of the children, be
all to God: who by his puiſſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hande hath ſo oftentymes deliuered and
conſerued this houſe of ours.</p>
            <p>If I do conſider &amp; waye the rarenes of my good fortune herin
(whiche doth preſent it ſelfe inceſſauntly before myn eyes: and wherof
I ſée my ſelfe vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſpoyled by this ſeparation) It can not
be, that I cane fynde here ſufficient or egall conſolation: when no man is
able to nomber by all the millio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that may be aſſembled, the infinitnes of
ſo notable a loſſe. I will therfore haue my recourſe to hym (if I dare
ſaye ſo) that hath geuen me the wounde, who ſhall, and pleaſe hym,
fourniſhe me of aſwaging plaiſter of his word to heale the ſame: as it
is ſaide of them that be bytten by the Scorpion, muſt ſeale the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die 
<pb facs="tcp:6224:10"/> of the Scorpion.</p>
            <p>And as to that ſhe prayeth me, by you, to double my good wyll
towardes our children: I dyd feale in my harte at the very ſame inſtant
that you ſpake theſe wordes to me, I can not tell what maner of hydden
infuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed in me the fyer of fatherlye loue: whiche I
dyd before beleue, coulde not haue receaued anye encreaſe, perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng
alwayes my ſelfe, that it was not poſſible to augment it in me.</p>
            <p>You ſhall now retourne, and ſaye to her, I pray you, that this
oratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whiche ſhe hath made me, by your mouthes, hath ſo reſolued me,
that I feale in me the effectes of the force of her noble cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage: and that I
do praiſe God great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the ineſtimable conſtancye, that he hath geuen
her: but I praye her that in any wyſe ſhe do not omitte nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake any
of thoſe meanes, whiche God hath departed to men by art and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie, for
the recoueringe of her health: to thintent ſhe do not leaue behinde her an
encreaſe of my ſorowes, when I <pb facs="tcp:6224:10"/> ſhoulde vnderſtande
hereafter the fault of her remedye.</p>
            <p>This diſcourſe was muche more great &amp; graue as you may
well thinke: but excuſe (I praye you) the memorye of a woman ſo
greuouſlye troubled and attainted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This done, ſhe cauſed two Notaries to come vnto her, vnto
whom ſhe ſpake from worde to worde her laſt wyll and Teſtament
commaundynge them to write in this ſorte followinge.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>COnſideryng the fragilitie and vncertaintie of this lyfe, and
that God, by this greuous ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes (wher wyth it hath pleaſed him to
viſite me) hath warned me as it were by a callynge vpon, to prepare my
ſelfe, &amp; to take order in my worldlye affaires, that I might be ready
with ſpede to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe his wyll, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſhall pleaſe hym to call me: I
haue made, ſayd, and ordayned, this whiche <pb facs="tcp:6224:11"/> followeth, for the
declaration of my laſte will and teſtament, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uokynge all others in any
ſorte made heretofore.</p> 
               <p>Firſt, I beſeche thee my good God, that when it ſhal
pleaſe thee to delyuer me of the miſeries and peynes of this lyfe, &amp; to
take my ſoule out of the priſon of this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye (wherin it is cloſed, but
for a tyme) that of thy goodnes &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, thou wylte vouchſafe to
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue it into thy handes, and to place it in the poſſeſſion and
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyinge of that felicitye, whiche thy deare Sone hath bought vs by his death
and paſſion: And by this meanes to aſſure, the ſtedfaſt faith,
which thou haſt geuen vs by thy promiſſes, &amp; ſealed, as wel by the
ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Baptyſme, as by the ſame of thy holy Supper, of the generall
remiſſion of oure <pb facs="tcp:6224:11"/> ſynnes: all whiche we beleue to be ſo
defaced by the bloude &amp; obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of thy Sonne, that they ſhall neuer
come in accompte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee.</p> 
               <p>Secondly, I recommende vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee our children, praying the, that
(accordyng to thy promiſſe) thou wylte be theyr God, theyr Father, and
protector: &amp; that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendyng thy bleſſyng vpon them, it may pleaſe
thee to illuminat, &amp; inſtruct them in the knowledge and feare of thy holy
name: and to ſerue thy ſelfe of them, as thou haſt donne of their father,
to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alte thy glory, to procure and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the reapoſe and quietnes of
thy churche, and to plucke vp by the roote al that which thou haſt not
planted therein: Make them by thy ſpeciall goodnes, inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and
veſſels of thy glorye, <pb facs="tcp:6224:12"/> &amp; repleniſhe them with thy
hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly graces, comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng them by the authoritie which thou haſt geuen me
ouer them, that they do aduowe and dedicate all their lyfe to thy ſeruice and
to the ſame of thy churche.</p> 
               <p>I referre the buryinge of my bodye to the good wyl &amp;
pleaſure of my Lord my huſbande, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wel that where ſo euer it doth
lye, it wyll reſte there in a verye certaine hope of his reſurrection.</p> 
               <p>Then ſhe diſpoſed her goodes to my Lordes her chyldren, and
gaue many charitable Legacies: And emongeſt others one for the entertaynynge
of the Colledge of <hi>la Ferté au Col,</hi> which a littel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my
Lorde her huſbande, and ſhe had inſtituted and erected.</p> 
               <p>She dyd alſo ordeyne that vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her landes, a certaine pencion 
<pb facs="tcp:6224:12"/> ſhuld be yerely leauyed towards the fyndynge of the Miniſters
of gods worde: and dyd her ſelfe heare the accomptes of al her ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts,
to thende ſhe might helpe them to that, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in any ſorte might be due vnto
them: ſo great was her care to do right to euerye bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, and to
vnderſtande her houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold affaires: wherunto ſhe wold be made preuye eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
vnto the laſt extremitie: geuing as good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in them, and with as ſounde
a iudgement, as at any tyme ſhe was accouſtumed to do in her moſt perfect
health.</p> 
               <p>That beinge donne ſhe cauſed the miniſter Perrucel to be
cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and declared vnto hym howe glad ſhe was to vnderſtand y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe
ſhold very ſhortly go to her God, by the ende of this ſicknes: And that
therfore ſhe woulde conſider <pb facs="tcp:6224:13"/> of the ſtate of her
conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: Not ſayd ſhe, thankes be to God, that I do feele my ſelfe
otherwyſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> well diſpoſed towardes my crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, &amp; readye to go to
hym when it ſhall pleaſe hym: but to the end that you father, whome god
hath ordeyned ſhepheard in my Lorde my huſbands houſe and myne, may knowe
the face of this ſhepe of your flocke: and that I dye contented, that I haue
geuen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Miniſter of the churche of the Lorde, a true teſtimonye
of my fayth &amp; hope of health, whiche by hys grace and goodnes I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue of
hym.</p> 
               <p>Then with ioined handes, and eyes lyfted vp on highe, ſhe made
humble confeſſion of her fayth: declarynge that ſhe dyd beleue &amp;
confeſſe God to be, and in beinge to be God only, diſtinct,
notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge <pb facs="tcp:6224:13"/> in thre perſons, which are the Father, the
Sone, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt: that he is creatour, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruer and gouernour
of heauen, the earthe, the Sea, and all that is in them: without whoſe wyll
&amp; pleaſure no creatures (be they Aungels, Dyuels, or any other) canne
make or moue any thinge: and yet neuertheleſſe he can not be ſayd, nor
ought to be ſayd, the procurer to euyll, or the cauſe or author of ſynne,
whiche doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceade of the corruption &amp; malice, that man hath
purchaſſed to hym ſelfe.</p> 
               <p>After this, ſhe proteſted that ſhe dyd not thynke, that ther
was any other meane or waye, by the whiche men might haue remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of
their ſynnes, health, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge life, but by Ieſus Chriſt only:
and that there is no other <pb facs="tcp:6224:14"/> name geuen to man for his
ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but that only: and that as he is very God, he is alſo only
ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour and redemer, mediatour &amp; aduocat of man towardes God, and ſole
ſacrificatour &amp; ſacrifice: who hath ones for all ſatiſfyſed &amp;
appaiſed the wrathe and ſtrayte iudgement of God the father, by his death
for vs, &amp; hath fully iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified vs in his reſurrection.</p> 
               <p>Wherfore I take him, ſayd ſhe, for my only and
notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng ſufficient ranſom, for my peace, for my wiſdome, for my
iuſtice &amp; for my ſantcfication: aſſuryng my ſelfe that he dyd
prepare a place for me in heauen, when he aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thyther, &amp; that he
doth there tarye me with his father &amp; mine by hym, with the holy Ghoſt,
the Aungels and the ſaints: where I deſyre to be with all my harte, 
<pb facs="tcp:6224:14"/> and whether I am ſure I ſhal go or it be longe,</p> 
               <p>Thyrdly ſhe gaue to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that we ought not to ſerue
God, otherwyſe or in other ſorte then as he hath appointed vs by hys worde:
And therfore that ſhe did acknowledge two partes in the true ſeruice of
God: Wherof the firſt and principall is to truſt and beleue ſtedfaſtly
in him: to obey his holy commandements: to cal vpon him in all our
neceſſities: &amp; to giue thankes to him onlye as the only author of all
goodnes.</p> 
               <p>Thother is to exercyſe in the churche thoſe thinges whiche he
hath eſtabliſhed: as the miniſtery of his worde and of his Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes,
the eccleſiaſticall Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline in her purenes, followynge his order
therin, withoute myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glynge eyther of the witte or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention <pb facs="tcp:6224:15"/> of
man: and therfore ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſynge her ſpeache a newe to God ſhe ſayd
further on this ſort.</p> 
               <p>Howe aboundauntly, oh Lord, haſt thou vouchſaft to ſhewe thy
mercies vpon me, that by thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſprite haſt made me vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and
ſee, that thy holy worde, the holy Baptiſme &amp; the holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per (whiche
be the two Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, that thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſte hath lefte to thy
churche his ſpouſe &amp; body) the diſcipline and correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of
ſinners, ordeined by hym in his Goſpel, be purelye and ſincerely
adminiſtred in the reformed churches of Fraunce: &amp; alſo that in the
ſame churches, the true doctrine of obedience, of repentaunce, of faythe, and
iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by the ſame, through the merite of Ieſus Chriſt
(wythoute that there may be anye thynge at <pb facs="tcp:6224:15"/> all allowed of ours
for payment) is there preached and conſtantlie declared: that Gods name is
truly called vpon there, that is to ſaye, in the onlye name of Ieſus
Chriſt: and that to hym alone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyuen al thankes for al his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
receyued:</p> 
               <p>For theſe cauſes I ſay, Oh my Lord, &amp; delyuerer, I do
acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that theſe reformed chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, with all other lyke vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
(wher ſoeuer they be) do make togethers the ſpouſe and the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of thy
So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne Ieſus Chriſt, thy choſen vyne, thy flocke, thy holy Ieruſalem,
and thy lawfull aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblye: thankynge thee wyth al my hart, that thou
haſte called me to this moſte happye know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: yea and I tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke thee
more, that thou haſte made me one of the ſtones of this thy buyldynge 
<pb facs="tcp:6224:16"/> &amp; humble Citie, one of the ſhepe of this thy flocke, one of
the brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of this thy vyne, and one of the members of this body &amp; and
of this ſpouſe of thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſt.</p> 
               <p>Make me ſo to perſeuere (oh dyuine goodnes) and continue in me
theſe graces euen vnto the laſt ſighe of my lyfe: to the ende that
accordynge to thy promeſſe, I may be receaued of the into the kyngdome and
heritage of thy moſt happy chyldren.</p> 
               <p>
                  <hi>The ende of the wyll.</hi>
               </p> 
            </q>
            <p>Wythin an houre after ſhe ſent for, and cauſed to come into
her chamber, the Miniſter <hi>de l' Eſpine,</hi> of whome I haue already
ſpoken to you: and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuynge (in one maner of feruencye &amp; affection)
the talke which before ſhe had entamed, ſhe began to recite the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours 
<pb facs="tcp:6224:16"/> whiche God had ſhewed her, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge as vnto the worlde made her
greatly honorable, and imparted large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inoughe vnto her of the goods of the
ſame: aſſiſted her in all her affaires, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended and ſuſteyned my
Lord her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande, my Lady her mother, her ſelfe, her children, her
kynſfolks and frindes, againſt all the enterpriſes and conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies of
their ennemyes: and yet that al theſe his graces, dyd ſeame lyttel vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
her, in reſpect of the knowledge which he had geuen her of hym &amp; of his
Sone by his holy worde: for in that only co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted al her felicitie, &amp;
it was the certaine and true foundation of all her hope.</p>
            <p>And being by all theſe reaſons infinitly bounde to ſerue
God, that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng ſhe had not done her dutye to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and
confeſſe the author fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whome ſo many and ſondrye bleſſyngs came
vnto her, to giue vnto him for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all thankes, praiſes and glorye.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe for all theſe greate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitudes which ſhe
had vſed towards God, ſhe dyd verely hope that by hys <pb facs="tcp:6224:17"/> mercy
and the merite of his Sonne the ſame and all other his fautes ſhulde be
entyerely pardoned, aſſurynge her ſelfe to be in the nomber of his
ſhepe, by the grace ſhe had receyued to heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> voice of her ſheppeard,
&amp; paſtour, and that by his callynge of her, ſhe was aſſured of her
Iuſtice and glorie.</p>
            <p>For theſe cauſes ſhe ſayd, ſhe deſired nothing more
earneſtly the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye out of this worlde, that ſhe might go into
the armes of her Sauiour: &amp; that notwithſtanding, ſhe dyd leaue behynd
her my Lord the Prince her huſbande, my Ladye her mother, &amp; my Lords her
children (whiche ſhe dyd loue as muche and as well as nature and dutye might
beare) yet ſhe preferred God to all them: And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there was nothing ſo
deare vnto her, as to followe redilye and cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye his good wyll and
pleaſure.</p>
            <p>The Dyuel ſhe ſaid dyd ſet before her eyes many ſondry
imaginations, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the kyngdome of heauen: &amp; went about to perſuade
her, that it was not the ſame that ſhe toke it to be, that by <pb facs="tcp:6224:17"/>
that meanes he might brynge her to be lothe to leaue the vaine pleaſures
&amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes of this worlde: But for al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, ſhe dyd remayne ancred in
that faith, that eye neuer ſawe, care neuer harde, nor harte of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could
euer conceaue, which god hath prepared for his elect.</p>
            <p>As ſhe had thus made an ende, came into the chamber my Lorde the
Prince (as he was very diligent in viſitinge of her) and after that he had
ſpent a fewe wordes, in the coumfortyng of her, ſhe ſayd vnto him, there
were fowre things which dyd greatly ſatiſfice and content her. The firſte
was the aſſuraunce, ſhe had of her ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for by the hope and hande
of fayth, ſhe dyd alreadye enioye eternall lyfe. Her ſecond contentation
was, in the reputation of an honeſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whiche ſhe had alwayes had, by
the grace of God. Thyrdly, ſhe dyd aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure her ſelfe, that euen, as
ſhe had as faythfully ſerued hym, loued hym, and honored hym, as anye woman
in the worlde coulde doo her huſbande: ſo ſhe dyd as verily beleue that
on his part, he <pb facs="tcp:6224:18"/> dyd holde hym ſelfe very well content, &amp;
ſatiſfiſed of her: And for the laſt point, ſhe dyd greatlye reioice,
that God dyd leaue ſuche a father to her children, and ſuche a Grandmother,
as would bring them vp in the feare of the Lord, which was the chefeſt of her
deſiers.</p>
            <p>My Lord the Prince could no longer abyde to heare this maner of
talke, and therfore after hauynge felte her poulſe, he retired hym ſelfe
vpon this worde which ſhe ſaid to hym: Syr, thus I muſt ende my courſe,
to wynne the price, whiche I ſée prepared for me at the end of the
lyſts of this painfull carire.</p>
            <p>After the Prince was thus retourned into his chamber, he ſent
vnto her my Lord Marquis their ſonne to make her merye, vnderſtanding that
ſhe had ſent for hym, &amp; that ſhe toke greate pleaſure to
ſée hym (as he is very amiable &amp; doth promeſſe many good
thynges, whiche ought to be deſired in a good Prince: When ſhe had aſked
hym howe he dyd, and the <hi>Seigneur of Garannes,</hi> his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, how he
vſed hym ſelfe: ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded <pb facs="tcp:6224:18"/> of him, yf he woulde not be
content, that, accordyng to the order of nature, ſhe dyd firſt go to God,
ſince it was ſo his pleaſure to call her, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge our Father, he dyd
nothynge but for our aduauncement and profit.</p>
            <p>I praye you my ſonne, ſayde ſhe, feare hym aboue all
thinges, &amp; honor hym as author of all goodnes: at whoſe ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des you ought
to looke for all fauour, ſince it hath pleaſed him to leaue in our houſe
ſo greate an earneſt of his beneficence, whiche you ſhall muche better
iudge with more yeres. Growe in vertu, my lyttel frynde, whiche is the true
orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great: to the ende you may be capable to do the Kyng agreable
ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: In whoſe face euery man may ſée the printe and marke of
a well borne Prince and of a litell Ioſias, of whome you haue harde me ſo
often ſpeake. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor my lord Cardinal of Bourbon, my Lorde your father, my
Ladye youre grandmother, your vncles my Lordes of Chaſtillion &amp;
Rochefoucault, whiche be men that feare God, and haue made <pb facs="tcp:6224:19"/> good
prouffe of their vertues in fondry ſortes: Loue well the common wealth, and
procure it by all iuſt meanes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offendynge your conſcience: Loue
your two brethern and your ſiſter, not as a brother, but as a father, for
ſo you muſt be to them, ſince you are the eldeſt and be no more a
child: Talke the ofte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte, that you may with the Miniſters <hi>Perrucel
&amp; de l'Eſpine,</hi> for your ſoules health, &amp; beleue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel of
thre me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Lawe, whiche you knowe to be beloued and eſtemed of my Lorde
youre father and me: Beware that you neuer do any thinge vnder collour or
procurement, that any man ſhall ſaye to you, that your gouernour (be he
neuer ſo watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful) ſhall not here nor knowe of it: For your Father who is
in heauen doth ſée, vnderſtand, and know all thing, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
you ſhould be aſhamed to do euell, as if he were alwayes preſent &amp; by
you, accordyng to the godlye inſtructions of your booke of Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which you
ſhuld neuer leaue out of your handes, to the ende that in all your lyfe and
conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <pb facs="tcp:6224:19"/> you may ſpeake &amp; recite to euerye body,
that whiche is conteyned therein: Be gentyll and tractable to ſuche as be
ſo: abatinge the pryde of them, whoſe audacitie ſhould make them forget
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfs: Let your mouth be the houſe of truth, your hande open to the
poore, &amp; your gates cloſed to flatterers.</p>
            <p>If you do this, my Iuell, you ſhall haue as Abraham, Iſaac,
&amp; Iacob had gods bleſſinge and mine: whiche I do gyue you w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this
ringe of Diama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that you ſhall kepe for my ſake, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of
that which I haue ſaid to you: Wherof your gouernour is wytneſſe, &amp;
canne wel put you in minde of it, in tyme and place conuenient, as he is moſt
carefull of your well doinge.</p>
            <p>She dyd then tourne her talke to my Lady her daughter, and wylled
her to marke diligentlye that whiche ſhe had ſayd to her brother: and that
ſhe ſhould beleue the councel and aduiſe of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye of ſainct Cir
her gouerneſſe, no leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as if ſhe were her naturall mother.</p>
            <p>Theſe lyttell children, whiche ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes <pb facs="tcp:6224:20"/>
kyſſed her mouth &amp; ſomtymes her handes, were by her commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
taken oute of her ſight, leaſt they ſhould haue bene made more
ſorowfull, and becauſe, with all that ſhe could doo ſhe could note
ſtay them by any meanes from moſt bytter weepynge.</p>
            <p>After ſhe had thus ſayd to her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſhe beganne with a
newe admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to her maydes and Gentilwomen: but you ſhall holde me
excuſed if I doo not tel you the hoole: for I dyd then go forth to prepare a
thing whiche the phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions had appointed for her: And I came againe, as
ſhe was praying the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good bringing vp and nour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riture which
they had had in her houſe, and the example whiche ſhe had geuen them: Haue
alwayes (my daughters, ſaide ſhe) the reuerence of God before your eyes:
and let your honor be more dere vnto you then your lyfes: Loue my Lady my
mother &amp; my daughter, for thei loue that, that toucheth me, and you ſhall
continue with them vntyl you be maried. Farewell my maydens: <pb facs="tcp:6224:20"/>
thinke me happye and contented, and learne you to dye wel.</p>
            <p>At night, féelyng her ſelfe troubled with a great
laſke, with a ſhorte breath, &amp; with a peyne in her throte, ſhe
cauſed the Miniſter Perrucel to come to her, &amp; to talke to her of God,
as oftentimes he dyd: and as he was in comfortynge of her, ſhe lifted vp her
handes to heauen, and with a ſofte ſighe, ſaid in this ſorte.</p>
            <p>Ha my God my Father, it is nowe that I ſhal come to thee: I haue
foughte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a good combat: I haue kepte my faith: I haue ended my courſe, and
all by thy grace and fauour: for the whiche, I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure my ſelfe that I
ſhall haue, or it be longe, the crowne of Iuſtice, and ſhall lyue of the
lyfe, that thou kepeſt for me, and haſt hidden for me in Ieſus
Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Then ſtretchynge out her hande to maiſter Perrucell ſhe
ſayde: Father, praye to God, to gyue me perſeuerance and encreaſe in all
his graces: that he wyll ſtrengthen me againſt all aſſaults and
temptations: that he wyl alwayes holde his hande ouer me, as I do ſée
he <pb facs="tcp:6224:21"/> doth in his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt: that he do make me
continuallye féele his loue towardes me, that he do deliuer me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all
grief &amp; ſorowe, which might trouble me for the leauynge of any
corruptible thing of this worlde, and that the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of my ſicknes, do
not hynder me from the magnifyinge of his name and hyghnes.</p>
            <p>In this ſorte ſhe ſpake to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, for that ſhe
thought her ſpéeche ſhoulde ſoone after be taken from her,
iudgynge the ſame ſo, by that ſhe felte inwardlye.</p>
            <p>So, as immediatlye after they had prayed, ſhe ſent for my
Lorde her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande, who was then a bed (for it was nere vnto one of the
clocke after myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night) and for all the requeſt that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame de Roye dyd make
vnto her, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the matter vntyll the mornynge, ſhe continued ſtyl in
the contrary, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng her ſelfe, as ſhe ſayd, that he wold not be
ſory to be wakened for ſo greate an occaſion: &amp; that it was not good
to tarye vntyll ſhe coulde ſpeake no more, <pb facs="tcp:6224:21"/> leaſt ſhe
coulde not declare vnto hym thoſe thinges whiche God had put into her
harte.</p>
            <p>Thus was my Lorde the Prince cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, at whoſe commyng al the
company gaue place, and ſuffered them to ſpeake together. I cannot declare
vnto you the talke that then paſſed betwexte them: for albeit I was very
nere, yet I coulde vnderſtande nothyng, her voice was ſo muche decayed, and
to tell you true, I dyd ſomtimes ſlomber, as you maye imagine, we had no
great reſt, neyther night nor day. I remember very well that this
diſcourſe betwexte them dured almoſte an houre, for it was nere the
breake of daye before they lefte of, and about that time ſhe was wonte to
fall to a lyttell reſt, as ſhe then dyd.</p>
            <p>In the afternoone her peyne dyd take her againe (whiche all the
mornyng be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was ſlaked) whervpon ſhe beganne to ſay to maiſter
Perrucel. It is, now, father, that God wyll haue me, wherof I do moſt
reioyſe: but alas I am ſory, that my ſhorte breath, &amp; the rume which 
<pb facs="tcp:6224:22"/> falleth from my brayne, do let me to praiſe hym: praye hym, as
you dyd this nighte paſt, that it maye pleaſe hym to gyue me a lyttell
reſpite to cal vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, not that I do deſier to lyue any longer, for he
knoweth my thoughtes, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the tables of my harte.</p>
            <p>So ſoone as the prayer was made, ſhe felte her ſelfe muche
eaſed, &amp; at the ſame inſtaunt ſhe gaue God thankes in thys ſorte.
Is it not thou (Oh immortall Lorde, mightye God, wiſe &amp; good) that
without the helpe of man appaiſeſt in one moment of tyme my trauaile and
peines? Oh ineſtimable goodnes, which doeſt make thy ſelfe to be ſo
openlye ſéene, touched &amp; féelte of me, fortifie my ſoule,
ſince thou doſt abate my body.</p>
            <p>In this ſorte ſhe continued a good time in praiſing and
thankyng of God: Afterwardes ſhe framed and made her prayers for my Lorde her
huſband, my Lordes her children, my Ladye her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for al the Churche,
and finally, for all them of whome God had moſte ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallye bounde her to
haue care: as her <pb facs="tcp:6224:22"/> kynſfolks, her frindes, her allyes, her
ſeruauntes and ſubiectes: which prayer was at the leſt an houre longe,
toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with the ſame, ſhe made for the Kynge, and for the tranquillitie
of the Realme.</p>
            <p>So great were then the ſorowes, we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynges, and lamentable voyces
of all thoſe that were preſent, that I coulde beare awaye neyther the
ſubſtaunce, nor the forme of it: but this I canne aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, that it
is impoſſible to heare more humble, pure and ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t prayers, then ſhe
made at that time: &amp; I knowe very well, that all the hole companye had
their hartes no leſſe heauy then I, whiche may be a ſufficient
teſtimonye to you of the ſame.</p>
            <p>In the ende ſhe aſked pardon of all the worlde, namely of my
Lady her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of her good ſiſter, Madame de Rochefoulcault, who was
ther with her as continuallye, as if ſhe had bene tyed to her.</p>
            <p>Whyle theſe thinges were in doing, there came vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her againe
greate diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie <pb facs="tcp:6224:23"/> for the takyng of her breath, with a ſore
griefe in her ſyde, whiche put her ſodenly to ſilence: but this euel dyd
im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly ceaſe by the remedie of praier: A thinge worthye of great
marueil: &amp; as ſhe her ſelfe did well acknowledge, at whoſe handes
ſhe receyued that eaſe and fauour. And I remember how cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſlye, at the
ſame tyme, ſhe cauſed <hi>l'Eſpine</hi> to recite vnto her the
paſſages of the Scripture, whiche be proper and mete for the conſolation
of them, which dye in Ieſus Chriſte: Of all whiche I wel bare awaye the
ſame of the Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipſe, and that of Eſaye in the laſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters:
whiche you ſhall for my ſake, and pleaſe you, rede ouer at your
leaſure.</p>
            <p>I wil not write you here the diuine dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues, that paſſed
betwexte her and my Ladye her mother, duryng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courſe of this ſicknes: as
of the greatnes of God, of hys wiſedome, goodnes and mercye, of hel, of the
conſciences of ſuche as haue not his feare before their faces, of the
difference of true &amp; falſe ſeruice, of the aſſuraunce of the
fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <pb facs="tcp:6224:23"/> ſoule at the article of death: And of ſuche other
highe matters, whiche well deſerue hole and longe letters: but I wyll kepe
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſtore for you againſt an other tyme: and beleue I praye you, that I
ſhoulde fynde my ſelfe greatlye troubled, if I ſhoulde come to gyue my
iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t whether of them ſaide better, For you know what ſwetnes there is
in the mouth of Madame de Roye, and howe graue her diſcourſes be.</p>
            <p>The night before the death of oure religiouſe Princes, about two
of the clocke after midnight, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Miniſter Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rucel (perceyuynge it
ſhoulde be verye harde for her to paſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day followyng) declared vnto
her (as ſhe had alwayes deſired hym) that the houre in his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion dyd
drawe nere of her departyng: that ſhe ſhuld be or it were longe at her
deſired reſt: that in any wiſe ſhe toke a good harte to her, without
hauyng feare of the lawe, of ſinne, of hel, or of anye other ennemie of her
ſaluation: that all ſuche theues and robbers had bene put to flyght, by the
Lambe of God Ieſus <pb facs="tcp:6224:24"/> Chriſt, together with the emperour of
death, the Dyuell &amp; his empyre, who was made curſednes and condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
for all them that put theyr truſt and confidence in hym.</p>
            <p>And when the Miniſter aſked her, if ſhe felte not her
ſelfe by the vertue and grace of the holy Ghoſte, armed of the pieces
whiche ſainct Paule writteth of, to the Epheſians: and aboue all of the
buckler of fayth, and the ſharpe ſworde of the worde of God: She
aunſwered, yea trulye father, I haue in my harte that whiche God, ſince my
youth, hath put in it, the aſſurance of my ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and ſo ſhe
ſayd theſe foure verſes of Dauid.</p>
            <q>
               <l>My Lorde my God by vertue thine</l> 
               <l>Ys made to flye this foe of myne</l> 
               <l>Diſcomfited of force and might,</l> 
               <l>At thyne aſpect and only ſight.</l>
            </q>
            <p>That donne ſhe continued her talke to maiſter Perrucel, and
ſayd therfore, father, aſke of god for me, and I wil in <pb facs="tcp:6224:24"/> harte
praye with you, that he wyll al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes lende me the burninge lampe, to thinte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,
that when the ſpouſe ſhalco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me, I may enter in with hym to the wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge:
that he wyll gyue me the grace to watche continually, to the ende, I be not
taken ſodenly, when my Lorde ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me: that he wyl gyue me the whight
garment, that I may follow the lambe with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyuerey, wherſoeuer he goeth:
that he wyl make me to be borne of his Aungels, that I do not falle, and that
he wyll take me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence belowe, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng his lefte hande vnder my heade,
&amp; embraſinge me with his right.</p>
            <p>Then they prayed, and aunſwere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made, ſo be it, ſhe
ſayd. Oh my god my Sauiour, now is my wynter paſt, and my ſpringe tyme is
come: Open therfore the gate vnto me of thy celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al garden, that I may
taſte of the fruit of thy euerlaſtyng ſwetnes: repetynge theſe wordes
thre tymes.</p>
            <p>At this ſame tyme maiſter Perrucell toke his leaue to goo, to
prepare himſelfe to preache, which he ſhould do that mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge, 
<pb facs="tcp:6224:25"/> &amp; in his place came <hi>l'Eſpine,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng as they
diſpoſed of the houres, to be about her, tourne by tourne, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: with
the miniſter <hi>la Boſsiere.</hi> It was then about .vij. of the clocke in
the morning, beinge Sonday .xxiii. daye of this moneth. <hi>L'eſpine</hi>
continued in prayers and exhortations, and as you knowe he is ritche and
copious in ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſons, ſo he ſpake things more
celeſtiall then humaine: whiche laſted for the ſpace of an houre, &amp;
vntill they gaue to this couragious pacient ſome lytell ſuſtenaunce: who
was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couſtumed to ſays .vj. or .vij. dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that
notwithſtandinge, ſhe knewe welinough, that that ſhe did eate &amp; take,
was vnprofitable, &amp; a loſt thinge, that neuertheleſſe ſhe would
ſtyll entertaine her bodye with nouriſhment, vntil it ſhould pleaſe God
to diſpoſe of the iſſue of her ſoule: and that it was not in vs to
leaue this gariſon without the leaue of our Captaine.</p>
            <p>Soone after this repaſt, her flux of bloud toke her againe,
whiche by no <pb facs="tcp:6224:25"/> meanes coulde be ſtopped, for that her forces were
ouermuche abated: ſhe her ſelfe dyd then alſo iudge, that the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
remedies, vinaiger nor boxinges coulde any longer preuayle.</p>
            <p>Maiſter Perrucel (being in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) was ſent for,
becauſe, before, ſhe had deſyred that in any wyſe he mighte be by her
in that extremitye, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, that <hi>de l'Eſpine</hi> was then
there with her. Her difficultye of breathinge came vpon her againe: and
ſeinge firſt her right hande dye, &amp; then her lefte, ſhe put them one
vpon the other, and ſayde to me, it is now, my good frynde, that I doo go to
god.</p>
            <p>Maiſter Perrucell came in greate haſte, and ſo ſoone as
ſhe had perceyued him, ſhe ſayd, my good father, ſpeake for me, do your
office, you haue had the charge of my ſoule, my hearyng is har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened, my
tonge fayleth me, but I wyl make you ſigns with my head, if I can not
aunſwere. Theſe two Miniſters vſed vnto her many godly &amp; conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
exhortations, as they be both notoriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye learned, &amp; full of zeale:
after whiche <pb facs="tcp:6224:26"/> they aſked her, if ſhe had wel vnderſtode al
y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had ſaid, &amp; whether her hart did ſo beleue it, &amp;
féele it: Yea I thanke god, ſaid ſhe, liftyng vp her eyes to heauen:
make your prayers for me, accordynge as you both knowe my ſoule
deſiereth.</p>
            <p>Which prayers ended, ſhe called vnto her one of her maidens of
her chamber, that ſhe loued very dearely, &amp; ſaide vnto her (to the ende
ſhe might receyue with all the contentations that ſhe coulde, the eaſe
and benefite of death) that ſhe ſhoulde take her legges, &amp; ſtretche
them forth, whiche the rigor of mortall colde had already drawen vp. And
ſodenlye ſhe pronounced theſe wordes.</p>
            <p>Into thy handes, oh Lord, I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende my ſoule: And ſo beganne
to enter into the pangs of death: wherin ſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued not ſo longe as
halfe a quarter of an houre, durynge whiche tyme, theſe two good men,
togethers with <hi>la Boiſsiere,</hi> dyd declare vnto her ſondry good and
godly ſayings, of the aſſuraunce of her ſaluation, and to aunſwere
them, &amp; to let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knowe that ſhe vnderſtode them well, ſhe enforced
her ſelfe to ſpeake, but <pb facs="tcp:6224:26"/> could not: ſo as ſhe gaue them
in ſteade of wordes the ſigne of the head, whiche ſhe had before
promiſed.</p>
            <p>Within a minute of an houre after, ſhe departed, by a ſwete
ſighe vp into heauen, into the heritage whiche God hath prepared for his
elect: Leauyng to vs all, a deſier to ende as ſhe had donne.</p>
            <p>I can not but tell you that, becauſe whylſt I lyue here, I
canne ſée her no more, I muſt remaine for euer in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame
ſorow and heauines, and yet in a ioye moſte greateſt, that I haue
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayned in ſeruice to ſo vertuous a Princes.</p>
            <p>Nowe cometh to my remembraunce the talke which maiſter Perrucel
had to this Ladye, at the article of her death, which I eſteame worthy to be
written.</p>
            <p>Madame, ſayd he, you muſt &amp; pleaſe you acknowledge the
goodnes of this great god towardes you: not only for all the goodnes &amp;
graces whiche he hath donne for you in all your lyfe hytherto: but alſo for
the ſpecial fauour which he doth preſently ſhewe you: for hauynge put you
into his vyneyarde, there to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure <pb facs="tcp:6224:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> &amp; trauayle all
the hole day, he wil take you from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, at the midds of the day, to bring
you to reſte and quietnes. You haue ſcantly yet attayned to the middes of
your age, which you haue by the grace of god, well &amp; faithfullye em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed
in the labour of his vyneyarde: Ought not you to thanke him, &amp; thinke well
of hym, if he wyll excuſe you of the ſweate &amp; traueaile of the reſt
of the day, &amp; gyue you lyke wages, and payme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as if you had laboured all
the daye longe.</p>
            <p>I had alſo forgotten to tell you, that about a moueth before her
death: ſhe ſayde to a perſonage of greate qualitie, her kynſma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and a
very iuſte man, that ſhe had hard a voice in the night, which ſayd to her
in very plaine wordes, that ſhe ſhould dye, or it were longe, &amp; that
therfore ſhe ſhould prepare her ſelfe: and ſo muche it lacked, that
thoſe newes did make her any thing ſadde or ſorowfull, as that euer after
ſhe dyd moſte deſier the ende of this holy ſeparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I muſt tell
you truly, that without flatterynge of thoſe of our ſexe &amp; ſorte, her
magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimitye herein, hath ſhamed, and put to <pb facs="tcp:6224:27"/> foyle the great
courage wherof men ſo ordinarily do vaunt them ſelues: for her members
dyinge one after an other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her eyes, ſhe dyd leſſe care for the
feare of death, then the braueſt of them euer dyd. She ſpake as francklye
and boldly of this great terror of death, as if it had bene of any thinge, that
euery daye is moſt comen to vs, and that doth appartaine to oure moſt
familier &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticall matters. And two dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her death,
notwithſtandynge, that the dangerous beatynge of her poulce did make her
perfect of that, which ſoone after ſhould come to her, neuertheleſſe
ſhe cauſed to be brought to her the plote of the caſtell of Amſi:
whiche ſhe had commaunded to be made a lytel before her ſicknes: wherin
ſhe did deuyſe with my Lord her huſbande, as curiouſlye, &amp; as
particularly, of all the deſſeins, deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and orders, as that you
would haue thought, to haue ſéene her ſpeake wyth her ordinary
laughyngs and ſmilyngs, that ſhe would haue accommodated her ſelfe to
haue dwelt there, ſome lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g time: And yet dyd ſhe not this, but that ſhe 
<pb facs="tcp:6224:28"/> knewe welinough, that her true &amp; moſt aſſured buyldyng
was in heauen: But ſhe ſayd it was not to be marueled at, if ſhe dyd ſo
ſpeake and deuiſe of all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as thoughe ſhe had not ſet at al
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her eyes, the daunger wherin ſhe ſawe her ſelfe: For that god had
geuen her the grace euer ſince ſhe had the knowledge of him, and his worde,
that ſhe dyd thinke, ſhe was as well ſubiect to death at one time, as at
an other: &amp; that the true chriſtian will alſo beleue, that therof doth
depende the greatnes of of his bleſſednes and contentation.</p>
            <p>She was borne at Chaſtillion, vpon the ryuer of Loing the,
xxiiij. daye of Februarye. <hi>1535.</hi> And was maried to my Lord the Prince,
the .xxij. day of Iune. <hi>1551.</hi> Of ths mariage be iſſued ſeuen
children in ſixe times of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: that is to ſay, thre daughters,
Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine, Marguerit &amp; Magdalene, and fowre ſonnes, Henry, Fraunces,
&amp; at her laſt deliuerye, Charles and Lewes, twynnes. Henry, Fraunces,
Charles &amp; Marguerit be lyuyng: God hath taken the others. She lyued
.xxviij. yeres .iiij. <pb facs="tcp:6224:28"/> monethes .xxvij. dayes and .xj. houres.</p>
            <p>In the time of her ſicknes, ſhe was vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited of many greate
perſonages &amp; good folks: namely of my lords her three vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of
Chaſtillion, who did to her al the good, godlye and charitable offices, that
were poſſible to haue bene deſiered.</p>
            <p>I will not here diſcouer vnto you the noblenes of her race, as
wel French, as ſtrange, for euery one vnderſtandeth it ſufficiently, and
you knowe as wel as I that of her fathers ſyde, ſhe is deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the
righte lyne, by the woman of Lewes the ſixth, Kynge of Fraunce.</p>
            <p>Yet I will write vnto you thus much more, which hath ſeamed vnto
me to ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>partaine to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, that goeth before, &amp; which you ſhall receyue as
vſurye of my good wyll. This death was declared to my L. the Prince, who had
retired himſelfe alone i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to his cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, &amp; was gone to bed after his
retourne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the preaching. At y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming vp of the Miniſter <hi>la
Boſsiere,</hi> (who was made meſſenger for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) he
ſuſpected, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche was in dede happened, neuertheles he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued
ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time in readynge in a booke of praiers, <pb facs="tcp:6224:29"/> which he had in his
handes: ſoone after, tourni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g his face towards y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſter, he aſked him
howe his wyfe did, ſhe is my L. ſaid he, with god, whether you ſhall go
alſo one day: At this worde he coulde not kepe hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſighing
&amp; ſorowing, In ſo much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two or thre ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tilmen, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſter
Perrucel, who then came in, were greatly troubled to ſée him in that
heauye caſe: &amp; yet neuertheles durſt not approch to breake of his
bitter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaits, &amp; lamentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, vntil ſuch time as a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain man
towardes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe, came vnto him, &amp; prayed him to reſolue &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte
himſelfe, as he had done in all his other great aduerſities, &amp; herevpon
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters toke occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of talke,
according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> largenes of the ſcope, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was offered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:
notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng, he remained for a good tyme ſylent, and after puttyng his
handker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyef to his face, he ſaid. He truſted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god wolde not impute
vnto him, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, &amp; that good men wolde ſupport him, in thoſe
his greuous paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: ſeinge that his ſorowes proceaded not, but of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
loue of vertue. That in very dedede he <pb facs="tcp:6224:29"/> had great reaſon to
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent him ſelfe, for the aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce he had of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good reſt of hys
deare wyfe &amp; moitye, who had dyed the death of a ſainct: but alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
he was excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable for his heauines, to loſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panye of ſo wyſe
&amp; vertuous a Lady, that had alwayes honored him aboue al things-&amp; loued
him ſo derely, as ſhe wold haue ſacrificed her owne lyfe for hym: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had
gouerned his houſe in all holynes, and brought vp his children in al
wiſedome, in rendering to him all due obedience.</p>
            <p>He added to this (turning his face to heauen) a lyttel prayer to
God: the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence wherof, as I was writynge this vnto you, is fallen into my
mynde in theſe foure verſes, without, as it were thinkynge of it.</p>
            <q>
               <l>It is I good Lorde, not ſhe hath done the faulte</l> 
               <l>And reaſon wold, that I ſhuld therfore gryeue</l> 
               <l>Yet I do wronge vnto thy prudence hault,</l> 
               <l>For to ſaye truth, I dye and ſhe doth lyue.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Here vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, after hauing deuotly vowed the reſt of his life in
the ſeruice of God, he ſent for my lords his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſired
to eate ſomwhat (for it was then paſt noone) he defferred to ſée
them <pb facs="tcp:6224:30"/> tyll after his dinner, whiche was, God knoweth, a ſmale
thinge, &amp; ful of ſighes and heauines.</p>
            <p>After grace being ſaid, his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my Lords Marquis &amp;
Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, with theyr ſiſter were brought i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: his daughter was
ſette vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his bed, &amp; my Lordes, his two ſonnes ſtode by him, whether
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> litel ſoules were no ſooner co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me, but they fel ſo into
wéepyng, that al thoſe that were preſent could not withholde them
ſelfes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, no more could my L. the Prince their father, &amp; as for me,
I can not now tel it you, but I melte awaye in teares.</p>
            <p>You ſhuld haue ſéene this litle Ladye (who is a liuely
picture of beautye) take my L. her father about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> necke, &amp; waſhe his
face &amp; berde with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aboundaunce of her teares, wythout hauynge power to
ſpeake to hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but in halfe &amp; broke; words.</p>
            <p>My L. her father vſed ſuche wayes to her, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in the end he
appaiſed her wée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, &amp; did drie her face with ſom prety
admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, mete for her age, whiche I will tel you, if I haue caryed them
well away. My daughter, we muſt wéepe no more, our good God wylbe
angrye with <pb facs="tcp:6224:30"/> vs: do not you reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you ſay to him euery
daye, Thy wyl be done, he hath taken your mother out of priſon, to ſet her
by him in libertie, becauſe he loued her wel, &amp; wyl you be angry with it?
he is ſo wiſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld neuer aſke why he doth any thinge: he hath
lefte you here for the image of her: &amp; as I haue loued her, aboue all the
women of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, ſo I wil loue you: but you muſt not be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the image
of her face, but alſo of her ſpirit and vertu: for although ſhe were
fayre of perſonage, it was nothinge in compariſon of her gentil &amp; wel
diſpoſed mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, which neuer did office, but of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie, no more then
her hart, her tonge, her handes, &amp; her eares. As you ſhall waxe great
&amp; growe, enquire dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlie, what maner of woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this good mother was: And
whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſhal here, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe neuer loued man but her huſbande, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe
dyd alwayes lyue without any blote of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſtie, yea without
ſuſpition, that all her doings &amp; countinaunces, haue bene holy,
chaſt, modeſt, playne &amp; vertuous: Then enforce your ſelfe, my
minnio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to reſemble her, to thintent god may aſſiſt <pb facs="tcp:6224:31"/> you,
as he hath done her, that euery bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy may eſteame you, and that I may loue
you more and more, as I wyll not fayle to do, if you be ſuche a one.</p>
            <p>Then he called to hym the Ladye of ſainct Cir, her gouernes,
&amp; embracinge her, &amp; her daughter <hi>de Foſſes,</hi> he praied them
to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue their care in the educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and bringyng vp of her, as one of the
thinges, which were moſte precious vnto hym.</p>
            <p>After this, puttynge his hande vpon my Lord Marquis head, my
ſonne, ſaid he to him, you are the firſte teſtimonye which God gaue of
his bleſſynge, and fauour, of the mariage of your mother and me, and the
greate encreaſe of our loue. Séeke alwayes to gyue me ioye and
conſolation, as you ſhall do, if you wyl followe the ſtepps, which your
mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath troden before you, in the way of vertue: Marke wel the path &amp;
tracke therof, leſt you loſe your ſelfe, and fall into the wayes of the
dangerous dedal of this worlde. The ſonnes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menlye conforme them ſelues
to the doinges of the father: but you ſhall principallye <pb facs="tcp:6224:31"/>
ſtudy to reſemble in maners and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue your mother. For one maye tell you,
&amp; you may ſomtimes here of youre father, and of his life, things which
you ought not to follow (as in others again you oughte to imitate him) but in
your mother (of the lyfe and death of whome God hath vouchſafed to ſerue
himſelfe) you ſhal finde nothing, that is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be followed and
ſtraitly kepte, as ſhe was moſt worthy to be placed in the firſt rancke
of the moſte vertuous wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. My ſonne, vertue hath made Princes, &amp; the
Heroicall dedes of their aunceſters, &amp; thoſe that were before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For
the reſt, we be all the children of Adam, of ſinne &amp; of death, to kepe
well then this principalititye, it behoueth vs to lyue vertuouſly, &amp; to
flée from vice, as a thinge moſt horrible and abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to all
noble hartes.</p>
            <p>Therfore, it is, that a Prince ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes thinke, that he
is in this worlde, as vpon a ſcaffolde, to be beholden of al folkes: So as
his fautes be more ſéene and marked, then theirs be that be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
him: And as a blote that in an other <pb facs="tcp:6224:32"/> part might be hydden, is
eaſelye percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the face, and doth make one di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed (be it neuer ſo
lyttel) ſo is it in the actions &amp; doinges of Princes, which be (howe
ſmallye reprehenſible ſoeuer they be) ſéene &amp; perceyued of
euery one, by the highe place in degrée, that they holde emongeſt the
commen &amp; vulgare people.</p>
            <p>Lo, my Iuel, how you may proſper, and ſo you ſhalbe to me an
agreable childe.</p>
            <p>Then in the abſence of his gouernor, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted him to the
charge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gneur de Buiſſon,</hi> whome he gaue hym for his
ſtuarde, praying him, that aboue all thinges, there were good eye geuen, that
ther came nere him, no conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnor of God, nor of the reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, whiche we owe
to his holy commaundements.</p>
            <p>On Sonday after, whiche was ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdaye her body was put into
the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre of her predeceſſours at Muret, without other pompe or
ceremonie, but that maiſter Perrucel dyd make an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celent Sermon vpon the
fifty ſeuenth chapter of Eſaye, wherat there was a <pb facs="tcp:6224:32"/> good
nomber of nobilitie, and people of the churches, nere there abouts.</p>
            <p>The ſermon ended, which was about nyne of the clocke in the
mornyng ſome parte of the Gentilmen went, &amp; fetched the body (which laye,
leaded in a hawle nere vnto that, where the preachynge was) and ſo brought it
to the place cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and made for the reapos, and reſt therof vnto the
conſummation of the worlde.</p>
            <p>The reſt of the nobilitie and people followed the body in order
to the graue, and ſo after retourned in lyke ſorte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the court of the
Caſtel, where maiſter Perrucel declared vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> howe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy a worke of
Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s they had done, by thys theyr accompanying of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to his
buryal, of the great edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the ſame was to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the churche: Howe
pleaſaunt a thing it was to god, &amp; how agreable to my Lord the Prince:
thankyng them all in his name, and in the name of all the kynſfolkes of the
deceſſed Lady.</p>
            <p>I could ſend you in this pacquet ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which
were ſent as wel <pb facs="tcp:6224:33"/> to my late deceſſed Lady, as to my lord
her huſbande, ſince her death, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt wyſe, learned and apparaunt
perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Chriſtendome: but I vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by your good kynſman,
that you haue had the copyes of them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other places.</p>
            <p>This is then aſmuche as you ſhall haue of me at this time,
prayinge you to excuſe my wyt, my eyes, my memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, my hande, and my penne,
all which in their natures and offices, do féele the ſorowe and peyne
of me, their paſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate myſtres: who it maye pleaſe you, may remaine
in your fauour and good grace.</p>
            <p>God graunt you to lyue wel, and to dye well in his Sonne Ieſus
Chriſt.</p>
            <p>From Conde, in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey of Brye the laſt daye of Iuly.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>1564.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your entyer and good frind to obeye you. I. D.
V.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
